Finding Aid for Church Of The Good Shepherd (Dearborn Heights, Mich.) records, 1953-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Church Of The Good Shepherd (Dearborn Heights, Mich.) records 1953-1998
Church of the Good Shepherd (Dearborn Heights, Mich.)
(in 4 boxes)
3.3 linear feet
06112 Ba 2
Church of the Good Shepherd (Episcopal) in Dearborn Heights, Michigan was established in 1954. In 1990, the church building was sold; and in 1998, the congregation officially disbanded. The records include a complete register of church vital records, parochial reports, and annual reports.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ) in 2006.
The record group is open to research.
The first meetings of the Dearborn Heights Church of the Good Shepherd, a congregation within the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan, were organized in 1954 by a group of determined women. St. Luke's Mission of Allen Park, Michigan sponsored its creation. The first service was held at Mayfair School in Dearborn Heights on 14 May 1954 with 60 in attendance.
Two acres of land were purchased at 4138 Williams Avenue and the first services were held there on 11 May 1958. The church attained a maximum membership of 520 persons in 1959. A groundbreaking ceremony was held for an additional building on 24 July 1966, though the congregation had dropped significantly, allegedly due to the shift of more affluent members to the northern and western suburbs.
In August 1971 the Bishop's Committee requested the removal of the vicar. When their request was denied, the committee resigned. At this time a large faction of the church left and attendance declined. Another upheaval occurred in 1974 when missing bingo funds escalated into a legal dispute. Financial problems were also caused by declining growth, the maintenance demands of the large building and property, and the 1975 threat by Urban Affairs to cut the church's funding. In September 1977 the vicar was asked to leave.
During the 1980's the congregation was stable but small with slow growth. A 30th Anniversary Celebration was held on 18 March 1984 and attended by the Rt. Rev. H. Irving Mayson, Suffragen Bishop of Michigan. From 1988 to 1990 Good Shepherd organized a hunger task force. The church sold its building in 1990 and a small group continued without a building until 1998.
The first vicar of the Church of the Good Shepherd was the Rev. Everett W. Francis (1955-1964), succeeded by Joseph F. Kalbacher Jr. (1964-1969), Nelson L. Adair (1970-1977), Frederick B. Jansen (1978-1982 and 1983-1987), Hope Koski (1982-1983), and Patricia Eichenlaub (1987-1998).
The records of the Church of the Good Shepherd are perhaps of most value for their genealogical information about church families. In addition, the records include a complete church register and an inclusive series of parochial reports, Bishop's Committee meetings, church school records, and annual reports. Church histories were written in 1959 and 1981 and a scrapbook spanning the life of the church combines pictures and newspaper clippings.
The records have been arranged into the following series: Registers of Baptisms, Marriages, Burials, Communicants, etc.; Administration; Membership; Activities; and Historical and Background Information.
Subjects:
Church of the Good Shepherd (Dearborn Heights, Mich.); Episcopal Church--Michigan--Dearborn Heights.; Dearborn Heights (Mich.)--Church history.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Dearborn Heights.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Registers of Baptisms, Marriages, Burials, Communicants, Etc.
  The Registers of Baptisms, Marriages, Burials, Communicants, etc. series (1954-1990) consists of five volumes (with index) and four files of loose records. This series also contains documentation of members transferring in and out of the church. With these registers is a binder containing information (such as names, birth dates) of families attending the church.
  - Combined Record Book: Rector Directory 1955-1987 Communicants, 1954-1959; Baptisms, 1954-1962; Confirmations, 1955-1958; Burials, 1955-1990; Marriages, 1957-1970 (Box 1)
    (volume no. 1)
  - Communicants 1959-1991 (Box 1)
    (volume no. 2)
  - Confirmations 1959-1990 (Box 1)
    (volume no. 3)
  - Baptisms 1962-1989 (Box 1)
    (volume no. 4)
  - Marriages 1971-1988 (Box 1)
    (volume no. 5)
  - Miscellaneous Vital Records
    - Baptisms 1960-1978 (Box 1)
    - Confirmations 1969-1977 (Box 1)
    - Marriages and Intentions 1968-1987 (Box 1)
    - Burials 1980-1990 (Box 1)
  - Membership Transfers In 1964-1990 (Box 1)
  - Membership Transfers Out 1964-1990 (Box 1)
  - Family Register (Box 1)
- Administration
  The Administration series (1953-1998) includes a very complete collection of Bishop's Committee minutes, a register of church services (which records attendance and offerings), parochial reports, annual reports, and a later set of financial statements and church correspondence.
  - Bishop's Committee
    - 1953-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1998 (Box 2)
      (includes financial statements)
  - Register of Church Services
    - 1954-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1998 (Box 2)
  - Parochial Reports
    - 1957-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1997 (Box 2)
  - Financial
    - Annual Reports 1954-1990 (Box 2)
    - Financial Statements
      - September 1983-January 1990 (Box 2)
      - January 1990-November 1995 (Box 3)
    - Agreements (vicarage, loans, etc.) 1980-1988 (Box 3)
    - Withholding Tax Worksheet 1991 (Box 3)
    - Bequest of Viola M. Wyatt August 1990 (Box 3)
  - Other Church Records
    - Church Correspondence 1980-1990 (Box 3)
    - Fire Inspections and Violations 1980, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Food Inspections and Violations 1980, 1982, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Inventory 1969-1980, 1990 (Box 3)
    - School Records 1954-1981 (Box 3)
- Membership
  The Membership series includes a non-inclusive collection of church membership directories.
  - Member Directories 1965-1989 (not inclusive) (Box 3)
  - Lapsed Members 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Altar Guild Members 1978-1986 (Box 3)
- Activities
  The Activities series contains a file of loose photographs, a newsletter, and records from a hunger task force.
  - Assorted Photographs (Box 3)
  - Bishop McGehee Fund 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - C.E.S.A. (Combined Episcopal Services Appeal) 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Hunger Task Force 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter 1967-1990 (Box 3)
  - Retreat Notes (Box 3)
- Historical and Background Information
  The Historical and Background Information series includes two church histories, a scrapbook containing photographs and newspaper clippings, and a scrapbook commemorating the church's thirty-year reunion.
  - "How Did We Get This Way?" October 1959 (Box 3)
  - Church Profile August 1981 (Box 3)
  - Thirty-Year Reunion Press Release and Notes 1984 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1954-1989 (Box 4)
    (includes photographs and news clippings)
  - Thirty-Year Reunion Scrapbook 1984 (Box 4)
    (includes photographs)